{"tossups": [{"question": "This man commanded the construction of Fort St. Simon during a 1742 Spanish raid on his colony. This man, who transported Methodist founder John Wesley to America, acquired land from Tomochici and founded Savannah. For 10 points, name this English colonist who created a haven for debtors called Georgia.", "answer": "James <b><u>Oglethorpe</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A prominent player of this instrument was surreptitiously recorded on the obscene \"Bus Tapes.\" Jo Jones played this instrument in the Count Basie Orchestra, and it was played by the leader of the Jazz Messengers, Art Blakey. For 10 points, name this jazz instrument played by Joe Morello of the Dave Brubeck Quartet, Max Roach and Buddy Rich, who used sticks while playing.", "answer": "<b><u>drum</u></b>s [prompt on <b><u>percussion</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In a painting by this artist, Ambrosio de Spinola receives the keys to a besieged Dutch town from Justin of Nassau. This artist of <em>The Surrender of Breda</em> also painted <em>The Rokeby Venus</em>. A dwarf in a dress is one of the title attendants of the Infanta Margarita in a painting by this artist. For 10 points, name this Spanish artist of <em>Las Meninas</em>.", "answer": "Diego <b><u>Velazquez</u></b> [Diego Rodriguez de Silva y <b><u>Velazquez</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "According to legend, Horatio Nelson\u2019s body was stored in this substance after the Battle of Trafalgar. This product was created as a way to dispose of the molasses created as a byproduct of the manufacture of sugar in the Caribbean. In the British Navy, Edward Vernon created the practice of diluting this substance with water. For 10 points, name this component of grog.", "answer": "<b><u>rum</u></b> [accept <b><u>grog</u></b> until mentioned, prompt on \u201calcohol\u201d]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This movement's \"first lady\" recorded \"Don't Sleep in the Subway\" and \"Downtown.\" Another act from this period, which sang \"Doo Wah Diddy,\" was Manfred Mann's Earth Band. This mid-1960s movement included the Dave Clark Five, The Troggs, The Animals, as well as The Rolling Stones. For 10 points, name this wave of England-based artists who achieved American popularity.", "answer": "<b><u>British Invasion</u></b> (prompt on \u201crock\u201d or \u201crock and roll\u201d or \u201cclassic rock\u201d)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This route's eastern half was used by people who split off onto the Mormon or Bozeman paths instead of finishing this route. This route existed for twenty-five years before it became suitable for wagon usage as far as Fort Hall. At the end of its use, it went all the way to the Willamette Valley. For 10 points, name this iconic route used by settlers to the Pacific Northwest.", "answer": "<b><u>Oregon Trail</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man forced Gustavo Leigh out of his government for demanding a date for transition to democracy. This man came to power after his predecessor nationalized the copper industry, and while in power he relied on a group of economic advisors called the Chicago Boys. For 10 points, name this dictator who overthrew Salvador Allende to take control of Chile.", "answer": "Augusto <b><u>Pinochet</u></b> [or Augusto Jos\u00e9 Ram\u00f3n <b><u>Pinochet</u></b> Ugarte]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Kicking Bear added a sacred article of clothing to this movement that was possibly modeled on the temple garments of Mormons. This movement, which wore supposedly bulletproof shirts, was founded by Wodziwob and popularized by Wovoka. For 10 points, identify this religious and social movement of 1890s Plains Indians whose practitioners were killed at Wounded Knee.", "answer": "<b><u>Ghost Dance</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "U.S. doctors worked with a dictator of this country to eradicate yaws. This country was evacuated by U.S. troops as the major effect of Franklin Roosevelt's \"good neighbor\" policy; Roosevelt claimed to have written this country's constitution. For 10 points, name this country where the U.S. intervened in 1994 to restore Jean-Bertrand Aristide to Port-au-Prince.", "answer": "<b><u>Haiti</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This author corresponded with Colonel Thomas Wentworth Higginson during the Civil War, which was the subject of her poem \"It Feels a Shame to Be Alive.\" She described a carriage containing \"eternity\" in another poem. For 10 points, name this \"belle of Amherst\" whose poems such as \"Because I Could Not Stop for Death\" were published only after her death.", "answer": "Emily <b><u>Dickinson</u></b> <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 4 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "This ethnicity respected administrators called <em>yangban</em> under a state known in Western sources as the \"hermit kingdom.\" This group defeated an invasion by Toyotomi Hideyoshi at Noryang. From 1910 to 1945, Japan occupied this group's land after deposing the Joseon dynasty. For 10 points, name this Asian ethnicity which now lives on a divided peninsula northeast of China.", "answer": "<b><u>Korean</u></b>s [or <b><u>Hanguk</u></b>-im]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This woman was one of the first district attorneys in New York's Special Victims Bureau,and she wrote the Democratic National Committee's rules on superdelegates. George H.W. Bush was accused of disrespecting her in a 1984 debate. For 10 points, name this first woman to run as a major-party Vice-Presidential candidate, appearing on the losing Walter Mondale ticket.", "answer": "Geraldine <b><u>Ferraro</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In October 2014, a court case was filed regarding a Firestone rubber plantation in this country's town of Harbel. This country was the origin of Thomas Eric Duncan, who infected two nurses after arriving in Dallas with ebola. For 10 points, name this country where president Ellen Johnson Sirleaf governs the descendants of resettled American slaves.", "answer": "<b><u>Liberia</u></b> [Republic of <b><u>Liberia</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This city has for decades been the center of the least populated metro area to be the home of a major American professional sports team. This city\u2019s team is notable for its ownership structure, which consists of numerous shareholders and a stock sale in 1998 to help renovate its notoriously cold stadium at Lambeau (<b>LAM-boe</b>) Field. This city\u2019s team name references an industry that was criticized in Upton Sinclair\u2019s <em>The Jungle.</em> For 10 points, name this Wisconsin city on an arm of Lake Michigan, with a highly successful National Football League team.", "answer": "<b><u>Green Bay</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s wife Vibia Sabina may have had an affair with his secretary, the historian Suetonius. He made Marcius Turbo Praetorian Prefect and employed the <em>frumentarii</em> as secret police. This third of the Five Good Emperors was succeeded by Antoninus Pius. For 10 points, name this Roman emperor who demarcated the northern limit of Roman Britain with his namesake wall.", "answer": "<b><u>Hadrian</u></b> [or Publius Aelius <b><u>Hadrianus</u></b> Augustus]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This event was enflamed when a court-martial acquitted Ferdinand Esterhazy. One person involved in this scandal was imprisoned on Devil\u2019s Island until key evidence against him was revealed to be forged. Emile Zola wrote the letter <em>J\u2019Accuse</em> supporting that prisoner. For 10 points, name this scandal in which a Jewish French army captain was framed for treason.", "answer": "<b><u>Dreyfus</u></b> affair", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This color names a \"democratic movement\" which supports former Kenyan prime minister Raila Odinga (<b>rah-EE-luh oh-DING-guh</b>). A river separating both Namibia and Lesotho from South Africa is named for this color, which inspired a \"free state\" in pre-union South Africa. For 10 points, name this color also used for the Dutch royal house and a citrus fruit.", "answer": "<b><u>orange</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This event was a failure of Brigade 2506, which landed at Playa Giron (<b>hee-ROAN</b>). Allen Dulles took most of the blame for this event, which was a CIA operation with inadequate military support. This event relied mostly on exiles and prompted its target to formally ally with the Soviets. For 10 points, name this failed 1961 invasion of Cuba authorized by JFK.", "answer": "<b><u>Bay of Pigs</u></b> invasion", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This man published regular weather data in his</u> </b><em><b><u>Meteorological Observations</u></b></em><b><u>. As he was</u></b> <b><u>less influential in his own time than Jakob Berzelius, it was Berzelius's endorsement which</u></b> <b><u>led to acceptance of his ideas. He was the first to state what is now called (+)</u> Charles's Law and form a theory about red-green colorblindness, as well as the law of (*)</b> partial pressures. For 10 points, name this early nineteenth century British scientist who popularized the modern idea of atoms.", "answer": "John <b><u>Dalton</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>The founder of this religion is depicted reacting to sweetness in the painting</u> </b><em><b><u>The Vinegar</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Tasters.</u> </b></em><b><u>Mystics within this religion formed the Five Pecks of Rice Society, which formed a</u></b> <b><u>breakaway state that followed the (+)</u> \"Celestial Master.\" This religion was believed to be founded by a 900-year-old man who was forced to write down </b><em><b>The Book of the </b></em><b>(*)</b><em> Way</em> before leaving for the West. For 10 points, name this traditional, non-Confucian religion of China.", "answer": "<b><u>Daoism</u></b> or <b><u>Taoism</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>A news photographer captured an assault on Richard Frankensteen, a leader of this</u></b> <b><u>union, by surrendering fake photo plates. This union, now led by Dennis Williams,</u></b> <b><u>represents many (+)</u> graduate students. This union, which operated a dedicated radio station, was involved in the \"Battle of the (*)</b> Overpass\" during its leadership by Walter Reuther. The 1937 Flint sit-down strike gave it official recognition. For 10 points, name this union of car industry employees.", "answer": "<b><u>UAW</u></b> [<b><u>United Auto</u></b>mobile <b><u>Workers</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Mehmet Ali A\u011fca attempted to assassinate someone holding this position. Eugenio Pacelli</u></b> <b><u>was criticized for his silence over the Holocaust while he held it. One of these people</u></b> <b><u>condemned (+)</u> contraception in </b><em><b>Humanae Vitae</b></em><b>. Karol Wojtyla was the first non-(*)</b> Italian to hold this position in over 400 years, and Jorge Bergoglio became the first non-European in over 1,000 years when he succeeded Benedict XVI. For 10 points, name this head of the Roman Catholic Church.", "answer": "<b><u>Pope</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This westward-facing building is the largest in a similarly-named city that also houses</u></b> <b><u>the Bayon, the Ta Prohm, and artificial lakes called</u> </b><em><b><u>baray</u></b></em><b><u>. Its cross-shaped Grand Terrace</u></b> <b><u>stands in front of five towers laid out like the dots on a die. (+)</u> Suryavarman II began construction on this site, which was first dedicated to (*)</b> Vishnu before it became Buddhist. For 10 points, name this tallest temple built by the Khmer empire, which appears in white on the national flag of Cambodia.", "answer": "<b><u>Angkor Wat</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>These things were first discovered using Charles Chamberlain's porcelain filters. By</u></b> <b><u>1910, Peyton Rous demonstrated their role in cancers. In 1892, Dmitri Ivanovsky</u></b> <b><u>demonstrated that these things caused the (+)</u> tobacco mosaic disease. Walter Reed found the first large-scale human consequence of these things, when he showed that one of them causes (*) yellow fever. </b>For 10 points, name this quasi-living genetic information vector that is not a bacteria.", "answer": "<b><u>virus</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "<b><u>At one of these events, a man denounced an idea as \"thin as a homeopathic soup made</u></b> <b><u>by boiling the shadow of a pigeon that starved to death.\" These events, which were held in</u></b> <b><u>towns such as (+)</u> Alton, Galesburg, and Quincy, failed to prevent the (*) </b>\"Little Giant\" from winning a Senatorial election. For 10 points, what were these 1858 clashes of rhetoric in Illinois, which set up a rematch among their participants in the Presidential election of two years later?", "answer": "<b><u>Lincoln-Douglas</u></b> debates", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This person was the subject of a \"nullification trial\" convened by Calixtus III. This</u></b> <b><u>person led troops that captured John Talbot at the Battle of Patay. After getting an</u></b> <b><u>audience with (+)</u> Charles VII, this person correctly identified the disguised king. This hero of the Siege of (*)</b> Orleans claimed to have visions of St. Michael and St. Margaret. For 10 points, name this woman who was burned at the stake after fighting for the French in the Hundred Year's War.", "answer": "<b><u>Joan</u></b> of <b><u>Arc</u></b> [or <b><u>Jeanne</u></b> d'<b><u>Arc</u></b>; prompt on \"Joan\"]  <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 4 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras \u2013 ONLY READ IF YOU NEED A BACKUP OR TIEBREAKER! </b> <b><u>One leader of this nation has attempted to re-nationalize its YPF oil company, while</u></b> <b><u>another formed the Triple-A death squad to counteract leftist elements. The Justicialist</u></b> <b><u>party in this nation split into three parts, one of which was led by former president Carlos</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Menem. Another leader of this nation was overthrown by Jorge Videla\u2019s junta, which then instigated the (*)</b> Dirty War. For 10 points, name this nation once headed by Juan Peron.  ANSWER: <b><u>Argentina</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}